<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>English Presbytery, or, An account of the main opinions of those ministers and people in England, who go under the name of Presbyterians published for the vindication of divers noble and worthy persons, who by papists, and their adherents are without any ground aspersed with that name : and also of those who indeed do hold those principles, appealing to the judgement of all sober Christians, what there is of falshood or unpeaceableness in them.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B20531</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5315</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9925</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15509143</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15509143</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52746</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B20531)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52746)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 867:14 or 1148:50)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>English Presbytery, or, An account of the main opinions of those ministers and people in England, who go under the name of Presbyterians published for the vindication of divers noble and worthy persons, who by papists, and their adherents are without any ground aspersed with that name : and also of those who indeed do hold those principles, appealing to the judgement of all sober Christians, what there is of falshood or unpeaceableness in them.</title>
                  <author>Collinges, John, 1623-1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Occasionally attributed to J. Collinges.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, with print show-through and loss of print.</note>
                  <note>This item is identified as Wing C5315 at reel 1148:50 and as Wing E3114 (cancelled in Wing (2nd ed.)) at reel 867:14.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Presbyterians --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52746:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Engliſh Preſbytery:</hi> OR, AN ACCOUNT OF THE Main Opinions OF THOSE <hi>Miniſters and People in</hi> ENGLAND, Who go under the Name of PRESBYTERIANS.</p>
            <p>PUBLISHED For the <hi>Vindication</hi> of divers <hi>Noble</hi> and <hi>Worthy Perſons,</hi> who by <hi>Papiſts</hi> and their <hi>Adherents</hi> are without any ground aſperſed with that Name.</p>
            <p>And alſo <hi>of thoſe</hi> who indeed do hold thoſe Principles; appealing to the Judgment of all ſober Chriſtians, what there is of <hi>Falſhood</hi> or <hi>Unpeaceableneſs</hi> in them.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>John 5. 4.</bibl> Search the Scriptures, for in them you think you have eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, and they are they which teſtifie of me.</q>
            <q>Carpere vel noli noſtra, vel Ede tua.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:52746:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52746:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Good Reader.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE <hi>Presbyterians</hi> being (as the <hi>Jewes</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> Acts 28. 22.) <hi>a Sect every where ſpoken againſt,</hi> and that by many who are ſo far from underſtanding what the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> are, that they can hardly underſtand or <hi>ſpeak common ſenſe:</hi> I thought it might be worth the while in a ſheet of paper to do as much for <hi>Presbytery,</hi> as Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> did long ſince for <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritaniſm,</hi> to which <hi>Presbytery</hi> is at leaſt a piece of a Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour. That I might <hi>vindicate</hi> thoſe worthy <hi>Noble men</hi> and <hi>Gentlemen</hi> who are thus <hi>aſperſed,</hi> (though wholly of another mind) and alſo vindicate thoſe who indeed are ſo from the <hi>Obloquy</hi> and <hi>Reproach</hi> they lie under, with many upon that account. We are come to that height of madneſs that if a man will not <hi>drink healths,</hi> he is a <hi>Presbyterian;</hi> though our Sons of the Church as oft as they do it, violate the <hi>Canons</hi> (I am ſure of one,) I think of two <hi>Councils</hi> (never yet null'd by any law of the Nation,) if men will not be <hi>drunk</hi> and <hi>Profane</hi> they are again <hi>Presbyterians.</hi> It is not enough for men to own <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> to hear <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, to receive the <hi>Sacraments according to our Church.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs he will ſay in every thing and do in every thing as his <hi>Pragmatical</hi> Neighbour will have him, he is a <hi>Presbyterian.</hi> I have heard that in a late <hi>Election of Parliament-men,</hi> a <hi>Clergy-man</hi> of ſome note uſherd in a company of Electors, crying out, <hi>No Popery, No Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery.</hi> The ſober Hearers wondered what he meant, none looking towards <hi>Presbytery,</hi> being in any <hi>nomination</hi> or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any <hi>pretenſions</hi> to the <hi>Election.</hi> That therefore men
<pb facs="tcp:52746:3"/> may be no longer abuſed with empty <hi>noiſes</hi> and <hi>clamours;</hi> Thou ſhalt from this Paper judge who are <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and have an occaſion offered thee to judge of them what they hold deſerving ſuch a <hi>clamour,</hi> as a company of ignorant perſons make. I have ſometimes been in company (though unknown) where I have heard ſome begin to clamour at this rate. But making this Reply; <hi>That I had often heard Presbyterians revil'd,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but could never underſtand, from any who uſed their tongues at that rate, what thoſe perſons were or what they held: deſiring them to inform me:</hi> But could never yet meet with any perſon would favour me with their notion of them. So that it is a perfect <hi>Non amo te</hi> Sabidi, <hi>&amp;c. Reader</hi> I have here told thee what a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> is. If thou beeſt not a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> I doubt not but upon deliberation, thou wilt ſay, ſuch a one may be a much honeſter man then ſome of thoſe who reproach them; and a tolerable Chriſtian, though in ſome things thou, and he are not of a mind. I would have a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> to be one that is able, and ready to give account of his faith clearly to every one that asks him. And if all thoſe of other perſuaſions were ſo too, I think the world of all ſuch as own the Scriptures to be the word of God, and their rule, will quickly be agreed. If ſome have a <hi>latitude</hi> to give to men a further power in the things of God, than others can: they have no reaſon to be angry with thoſe that are more ſtraitned; for we have no reaſon all to cry out againſt the <hi>Pope</hi> for his claim to infallibility if we will not allow that we or any Church may be miſtaken. Farewell good <hi>Reader!</hi> and do but talk of, uſe and treat <hi>Presbyterians</hi> as thou haſt them here deſcribed to thee, and <hi>ſpeak</hi> and do thy worſt; and if thou ſpeakeſt otherwiſe thou doeſt but abuſe thy ſelf by <hi>lying or ſpeaking Evil of the things thou doeſt not know. Presbyterians</hi> are not concerned in thy Railleries.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52746:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Engliſh Presbytery.</hi> Concerning the <hi>Fundamental Principles of Difference</hi> BETWEEN <hi>Non-Conformiſts,</hi> Eſpecially ſuch as are called Presbyterians, And Others.</head>
            <p>THere are <hi>three fundamental Principles</hi> held by <hi>Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts</hi> (and thoſe eſpecially of them which are called <hi>Presbyterians</hi>) wherein they differ from others.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That the Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament</hi> are a <hi>perfect Rule for Chriſtians, directing them not only what to believe in the things of God, but alſo what to do in all matters relating to the Worſhip of God, and the Government of the Church; ſo as in theſe things they may not either believe or do what is not there expreſly, or by immediate conſequence revealed.</hi> In Civil matters they believe the Scripture to be only a <hi>general Rule,</hi> or rather as to them, to contain ſome <hi>General Rules</hi> only, by which all mens actions are to be direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but in <hi>Sacred things,</hi> they believe the Scriptures to be a <hi>particular Rule,</hi> both as to <hi>Acts,</hi> and <hi>Means,</hi> and <hi>Modes;</hi> ſo as it is the Will of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52746:4"/> God, that in them nothing ſhould be done but what is there direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and what is neceſſary to ſuch actions, conſidered as humane acts, and common to them, with all other humane acts, ought to be left at liberty, or ſo commanded, as they may be done without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to the General Rules of holy Writ, by which all humane acts are to be guided, <hi>viz.</hi> ſo as <hi>God may be moſt glorified, others moſt edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> and <hi>leaſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſcandalized.</hi> Thus they differ from <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who will not allow the Scriptures to be a <hi>Perfect Rule</hi> as to matters of <hi>Faith;</hi> and from thoſe, who although they allow them in <hi>matters of Faith</hi> a <hi>Perfect Rule,</hi> yet deny them to be ſo in the <hi>matters of Worſhip,</hi> or <hi>Government of the Church;</hi> and as to the firſt, ſay, That the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are only a perfect Rule as to <hi>Acts of Worſhip,</hi> not as to <hi>Means,</hi> and <hi>Modes,</hi> or <hi>Religious Rites uſed in,</hi> and about the <hi>Worſhip of God;</hi> but that theſe may be directed by Superiours for <hi>Spiritual Edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> or who ſay, <hi>That the Scripture hath only directed, That the Church ſhould be governed,</hi> but hath left to <hi>Superiours</hi> to determine by what <hi>Officers, Acts and Rules</hi> that <hi>Government</hi> ſhould be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed: So as the firſt and main Queſtion is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Whether the Scriptures be a perfect and ſufficient Rule for Chriſtians in matters of Worſhip, and Church Government, as well as matters of Faith?</hi> which thoſe called <hi>Presbyterians</hi> believe it is; becauſe they find <hi>ſufficient Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> in it for the <hi>decent and orderly performance of all Acts of Worſhip, without any humane<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſupplements;</hi> and <hi>ſuch Church-Officers directed</hi> by it, <hi>ſuch acts of Juriſdiction</hi> and <hi>Cenſures</hi> preſcribed in it, as are ſufficient to preſerve the <hi>Unity, Peace</hi> and <hi>Purity</hi> of the <hi>Church;</hi> which are the great ends of that <hi>Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, <hi>That the Ultimate Judgment of the Will of God revealed in Scripture, as to any perſons particular practice, is his own practical Judgment or Conſcience, after a due Enquiry into Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and comparing Scripture with Scripture, and hearing and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Judgments of others, as to things, the believing or not believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, doing or not doing of which, may render his ſoul guilty before God.</hi> And that although a man's Conſcience may err (as any other creature may) yet no Chriſtian ought to act contrary to the dictate of it, whether it dictateth upon probable, or demonſtrative Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in <hi>obedience</hi> to any man, but ought rather <hi>patiently to ſuffer</hi> any thing ſhall be impoſed on him for not doing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That where any things in the Worſhip of God are of <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52746:4"/> uſe,</hi> though they have been abuſed to the <hi>Worſhip of Idols,</hi> yet the uſe of them is to be <hi>retained,</hi> and the <hi>abuſe</hi> only taken away; but where the uſe of any thing in the <hi>Worſhip of God is not neceſſary,</hi> if it hath been ordinarily uſed in an Idolatrous Worſhip, it ought to be <hi>wholly diſuſed,</hi> eſpecially if it <hi>giveth an offence to any conſiderable num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Chriſtians;</hi> nor can the commands of any Superiours legitimate the uſe of any ſuch <hi>Rites, Figures, Habits</hi> or <hi>Actions; Superiours</hi> being obliged in the firſt place by the will of God not to <hi>command them;</hi> and being as much under the <hi>Royal Law of Love,</hi> as private perſons. Theſe are the <hi>Fundamental Principles</hi> of all thoſe truly called <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians,</hi> from which flow all their different <hi>Apprehenſions,</hi> relating to the <hi>Worſhip of God,</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>Miniſters of it,</hi> and the <hi>Miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in it.</hi> The <hi>Cenſures</hi> and <hi>Power of the Keys,</hi> which I ſhall now more particularly declare.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Divine Worſhip.</head>
               <p n="1">1. DIvine Worſhip (ſo far as it concerneth the outward man) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing elſe but <hi>the homage of the creature paid to his Creator, with reſpect to his excellency, and as an indication of the more internal homage of his ſoul,</hi> they can allow nothing as an <hi>Act,</hi> or <hi>Mean,</hi> or <hi>Mode</hi> of <hi>True Worſhip,</hi> under the Goſpel, but what <hi>Chriſt hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed,</hi> or <hi>exemplified,</hi> by himſelf, or his Apoſtles, or is juſtified by ſome Precepts or Examples in the <hi>New Teſtament;</hi> Chriſt having a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed both the <hi>Typical</hi> and <hi>Carnal Ordinances,</hi> by which it pleaſed God to command his peoples expreſſion of their homage to him under the <hi>Old Teſtament.</hi> And the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> mentioning only <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Praiſe, Reading, Preaching,</hi> and <hi>Hearing of the Word, Adminiſtring</hi> and <hi>Receiving Baptiſm</hi> and the <hi>Lord's Supper;</hi> they can allow theſe, and <hi>theſe</hi> alone to be the Acts of Worſhip, unleſs others can be ſhewn there.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Word of God directing the <hi>Form and Manner of Receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Adminiſtring both Sacraments,</hi> they believe they ought to be <hi>adminiſtred</hi> and <hi>received</hi> according to <hi>thoſe Forms,</hi> and no other; adding only the <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> and <hi>Praiſe,</hi> which are general acts of Worſhip, applicable in the uſe of any creatures. The Word of God alſo directing the matter both of <hi>Prayer and Preaching,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing no <hi>Forms of words</hi> for either, but requiring Miniſters to <hi>ſtudy</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:52746:5"/> to <hi>ſtir up their gifts;</hi> and, <hi>as they have received them, ſo to miniſter the ſame.</hi> They believe that Miniſters are both to <hi>preach and pray</hi> in the <hi>exerciſes</hi> of <hi>thoſe gifts,</hi> which God hath given them for that end: and to <hi>adminiſter the holy Sacraments</hi> according to his <hi>direction,</hi> without any unneceſſary variation. In keeping cloſe to Chriſt and his Apoſtles Precepts and Practice they know they cannot err: But they believe, that varying from it, they muſt err: Not allowing God the <hi>prerogative,</hi> which every creature challengeth, to preſcribe his own homage, and reflecting upon the <hi>Wiſdom of Chriſt,</hi> as if he had not known his Father's will, or <hi>not faithfully revealed it;</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> as worſhiping God in an <hi>imperfect manner,</hi> in the moſt <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>primitive times.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. They believe <hi>that nothing in the Worſhip of God which is idle, and ſuperfluous, is lawful,</hi> it being too ſolemn an action to trifle in: And that <hi>nothing can be added by man for Edification,</hi> (the Spirit of God alone being authorized to direct means in order to that end;) and that <hi>no Action, Rite, Figure, Habit, or any thing of that nature can be religiouſly uſed, by vertue of any Civil command.</hi> Nor can they underſtand how <hi>actions</hi> can be done in the <hi>ſolemn Worſhip of God</hi> meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>obedience to man,</hi> without confounding of things <hi>Civil and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred,</hi> and ſetting up <hi>Man's poſts by God's poſts,</hi> and <hi>Man's threſholds</hi> by <hi>God's threſholds;</hi> and endangering peoples ſuperſtitious apprehenſions in a ſhort time (as is abundantly proved by the Popiſh Worſhip) that theſe things are <hi>indeed acts of Worſhip,</hi> and upon that account <hi>accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table</hi> unto <hi>God:</hi> So that they have no ſmall apprehenſion that they leſs err, who (through ignorance) eſtabliſh ſuch things as <hi>parts and acts of Worſhip,</hi> than thoſe who require them to be mixt with true acts of Worſhip, but require them only under the notion of <hi>acts of homage</hi> and <hi>obedience to men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. More particularly, they do not think any <hi>geſtures, forms, actions, figures, habits,</hi> or any ſuch thing not <hi>neceſſary</hi> from the <hi>light of nature,</hi> or a <hi>Divine Precept,</hi> if they have been ordinarily uſed in the Idolatrous Worſhip of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> are lawful to be uſed by them in the Worſhip of God; becauſe they believe <hi>Papiſts</hi> moſt groſs <hi>Idolaters,</hi> and find themſelves confeſſing it, upon ſuppoſition that there is no <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation.</hi> And as God ſeverely forbad the <hi>Jews</hi> all Idolatrous uſages in his Worſhip; ſo the Apoſtle determineth the unlawfulneſs of <hi>Idolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thytes;</hi> and in this they have the Judgment of <hi>Tertullian</hi> very copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52746:5"/> But they otherwiſe judge of what is of <hi>Divine Institution,</hi> though ſo abuſed by Idolaters, and of what hath been uſed by them as <hi>conveniencies</hi> for <hi>Religious actions,</hi> though no more proper to them, than to ſuch as are civil, ſuch as capacious buildings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. They do believe <hi>Preaching</hi> to be the <hi>Explication</hi> and <hi>Application of the holy Scriptures,</hi> in order to <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Holineſs,</hi> and that it ought to be by <hi>comparing Scripture with Scripture;</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> working upon <hi>Scripture Principles;</hi> and that thoſe who only diſcourſe <hi>moral propoſitions,</hi> proving them from meer <hi>natural Principles,</hi> and the <hi>Opinions of Heathen Philoſophers,</hi> and the <hi>Teſtimonies of Men,</hi> are very far from diſcharging the duty of Miniſters in Preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, as thoſe alſo who deliver their diſcourſes in a ſtile and phraſe not underſtood by their hearers, and ſerving only to pleaſe and <hi>tickle</hi> the Ears.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Church.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THey believe that the term <hi>Church,</hi> in a <hi>Religious ſenſe,</hi> is to be interpreted only by the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and applyed only to a number of people, whom the holy Scriptures dignifie by that <hi>Title;</hi> and that we had not known the term, but for the Scriptures, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to a Religious Society.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They believe, <hi>that according to the Scriptures, the Church</hi> (moſt ſtrictly and properly) <hi>ſignifieth that number of people of whom Christ is the Head,</hi> and <hi>who are his Members,</hi> to whom belong the promiſes of all ſpiritual things, and of <hi>Eternal Life</hi> and <hi>Salvation;</hi> and this is the <hi>Church Inviſible</hi> (for the <hi>Lord alone</hi> knoweth who are his) part of whom are <hi>in Patriâ,</hi> their ſouls being already with Chriſt in glory (who are therefore called the Church <hi>Triumphant</hi>) having conquered all their <hi>Spiritual Enemies;</hi> part of them yet <hi>in Via,</hi> in the way to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven; or being choſen of God, are daily coming into that way, in which they have, and ſhall have the certain conduct of the Spirit of God, until they come to their Journeys end; but, till that time, will be <hi>fighting the good fight,</hi> with the <hi>World,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> and are therefore called, <hi>The Church Militant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. God alone knowing theſe, they believe <hi>that all thoſe who have given up their names to Christ, and are baptized in his name,</hi> making an <hi>outward profeſſion of Faith,</hi> in the <hi>Doctrine of the Goſpel,</hi> and <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Precepts of it,</hi> make up the <hi>Viſible Church,</hi> and are in Scripture
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52746:6"/> called, the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>Churches;</hi> and herein they agree with the ninteenth <hi>Article</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which truly ſaith, <hi>That the viſible Church of Christ, is the Congregation of the Faithful, in which the pure Word of God is Preached, and the Sacraments duly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministred, according to Christ's Ordinance, in all thoſe things that are of neceſſity requiſite to the ſame.</hi> That the whole number of theſe ſcattered over the whole world, make the <hi>Univerſal Viſible Church,</hi> and that the number of theſe, in any <hi>Nation,</hi> make up the <hi>National Church</hi> of this or that Nation.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They believe, that Chriſt hath appointed <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel</hi> for Officers to this <hi>Viſible Church,</hi> who may <hi>Preach the Goſpel,</hi> and <hi>Baptize</hi> in any parts of it; but can only exerciſe an <hi>ordinary juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> in thoſe particular parts of it over which God hath given them a particular <hi>Overſight</hi> as <hi>Pastors and Teachers;</hi> the exerciſe of <hi>Acts of Juriſdiction,</hi> requiring a particular knowledge of perſons Opinions, Knowledge and Converſation, which no ſingle perſon can have as to all the Members of the <hi>Viſible Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. They believe, that <hi>Ministers</hi> ought to be made by thoſe that are <hi>Ministers ordinarily;</hi> firſt <hi>proving</hi> thoſe that deſire <hi>that Office,</hi> whether God hath called them to it, by fitting them with his <hi>gifts and graces,</hi> for the performance of the ſeveral acts of that Office: Then <hi>ſolemnly ſetting them apart to it</hi> by <hi>Faſting,</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> and <hi>Impoſition of Hands;</hi> not as a token of their then <hi>receiving the Holy Ghoſt</hi> (as the Apoſtles uſed it) but as a <hi>token of their ſeparation to the work of the Miniſtry.</hi> In a total corruption of the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> or a want of Miniſters, they believe that a <hi>faithful people</hi> may <hi>prove</hi> and <hi>ſet apart</hi> perſons to the Miniſtry; that no Ordinance of God may be loſt which he hath given to his Church; ſo that none to prove their Miniſtry need run to an <hi>Apoſtolical Succeſſion</hi> impoſſible to be ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorily made out by the greateſt pretenders to it (which are the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts) or <hi>pleaders</hi> for it.</p>
               <p n="6">6. They believe <hi>perſons thus ſet apart to the Miniſtry, are fully authorized to Preach the Goſpel, and to baptize in any place where they are called to it, and to adminiſter the Lord's Supper, when they ſhall be fixed in any Congregation, that they may adminiſter it knowingly to perſons that are able to diſcern the Lord's body;</hi> and whoſe <hi>converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are ſuch</hi> as they may <hi>charitably</hi> judge them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>members of Chriſt,</hi> who ſhall not <hi>eat and drink unworthily;</hi> as alſo authorized to <hi>joyn
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52746:6"/> with</hi> other Miniſters in <hi>ſetting apart of Perſons to the Miniſtry,</hi> and to exerciſe <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>juriſdiction</hi> in their fixed congregation, admoniſhing the <hi>erroneous, ignorant,</hi> and <hi>ſcandalous,</hi> withholding the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> from them till they give ſome evidence of their <hi>Reformation,</hi> and caſting them out of the Communion of the Church if after <hi>admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions, inſtructions,</hi> and <hi>patient waiting</hi> they ſhall at laſt appear <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. They believe that Miniſters of the Goſpel are bound to <hi>pray</hi> and to <hi>preach in the exerciſe of thoſe abilities,</hi> which God hath given them for the work of the Miniſtry; and to <hi>adminiſter the Sacraments, and acts of Juriſdiction, according to the rule God hath ſet them in his Word,</hi> and no otherwiſe; for they are <hi>Miniſters of Chriſt,</hi> not of men, and <hi>Stewards of the myſteries</hi> of God <hi>of whom it is required that they ſhould be faithful,</hi> 1 Cor. 4. 2.</p>
               <p n="8">8. They believe any number of Chriſtians living in the ſame City, (ſo agreeing,) or in the ſame <hi>Pariſh,</hi> or <hi>Neighbourhood,</hi> may <hi>call</hi> or <hi>chuſe</hi> any perſons to be their <hi>Paſtor and Teacher,</hi> or <hi>Paſtors and Teachers,</hi> who may either ſingly, or joyntly take the care of ſuch a flock; and perform all Miniſterial acts towards them, either meeting in one, or more places for worſhip, ordinarily; provided ſuch perſons be either Miniſters before <hi>proved, and ſet apart</hi> to the Miniſtry, or ſo <hi>ſet apart</hi> before they take upon them that Paſtoral charge of ſuch Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but we believe no Perſon can be ſo called and ſet apart, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the rule of Scripture, but he who is <hi>ſound in the faith, of an unblameable life, apt to teach, and furniſhed with abilities both</hi> to <hi>pray</hi> and to <hi>preach,</hi> and that all <hi>callings</hi> of <hi>other perſons</hi> ought to be <hi>rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> and adjudged <hi>Nullities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. Our Saviour having determined Miniſters to be the <hi>Salt of the Earth,</hi> and that if the Salt <hi>hath loſt its ſavour, it is good for nothing, but to be thrown upon the dunghill:</hi> They do believe that he hath left a power, both in the Church, (if there be no Chriſtian Magiſtrate) and with the <hi>Chriſtian Magiſtrate</hi> (who is to be a nurſing Father to the Church) if any called to or placed in the Miniſtry, appear to be <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound in the Faith, ſcandalous in his life; Inſufficient for his work; Or negligent in the performance of it; to admoniſh</hi> ſuch perſons, and in caſe he reformeth not to remove him from the Miniſtry, who may for no other cauſe be removed from it, either by the Magiſtrate or the Church.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:52746:7"/>10. They believe <hi>That no Miniſter can be over more places, than he can diſcharge his Duty to, and he can reſide amongſt;</hi> and that all Miniſters ought ordinarily to reſide with their People, or ſo near to them, that they may perform the ſeveral acts of his Miniſtry to them, and that he can delegate that truſt to no others: Being him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf but a delegate from Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="11">11. They do believe <hi>by the Law of Chriſt, no Miniſter of the Goſpel is Superiour to, or hath further power than another, but</hi> all are equally obliged and authorized to <hi>Pray</hi> and <hi>Preach,</hi> and <hi>Baptize, and</hi> to <hi>give the Sacrament of the Lords Supper in</hi> that due order, which the Scriptures have preſcribed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. But in regard, That the <hi>Judgment of perſons fitneſs or unfitneſs for the receiving the Supper of the Lord,</hi> is a <hi>matter of great moment,</hi> they cannot judge it the will of God that it ſhould be left to the <hi>paſſions</hi> and <hi>Infirmities</hi> of <hi>any ſingle perſons.</hi> It being therefore appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently the will of God, that <hi>ignorant perſons,</hi> and ſuch as are <hi>ſcandalous</hi> ſhould be ſecluded, and ſo adjudged by all <hi>Reformed Churches:</hi> They do think that the <hi>Judgment</hi> in this caſe ought to <hi>be by more than one.</hi> Whether (if there be ſeveral Miniſters in the ſame congregation) it be done by more Miniſters, or by the <hi>Paſtor, or Paſtors,</hi> with ſome of the <hi>ableſt members</hi> choſen by the reſt to aſſiſt in that Judgment, they do not think ſo clear in Scripture, as to contend for; onely they generally judge theſe two things of <hi>Divine right in</hi> the caſe, 1. That <hi>a judgment be made to ſeparate the unworthy from the worthy. 2. That it be not the Judgment of any ſingle perſon</hi> but of more, whether <hi>Miniſters</hi> or <hi>People.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. Becauſe both the <hi>turning out of unfitting Miniſters, and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting perſons into the Miniſtery,</hi> and <hi>the caſting out of any perſons, by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, and the hearing of the complaints of thoſe who ſhall judg themſelves injured by any act of juriſdiction,</hi> be all of them matters of High conſequence; They cannot think them fit to be done and finally determined by the <hi>Officers</hi> of any <hi>particular congregation,</hi> but by the Officers of <hi>ſeveral Churches.</hi> And if, for order ſake, the <hi>Civil Magiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate</hi> (being a Chriſtian) ſhall pleaſe; Or the Officers of ſeveral Congregations with the Conſent of the Civil Magiſtrate, ſhall pleaſe in ſeveral Precincts to appoint a number of the moſt <hi>grave and pious Miniſters</hi> to judge <hi>as to the caſting out of any Miniſters,</hi> and to <hi>prove</hi> and <hi>ordain</hi> ſuch as ſhall be received into the Miniſtry, and to hear the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52746:7"/> complaints of any ſuch as judge themſelves injured; and if the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate will pleaſe to ordain, that one perſon (as his Commiſſioner) dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified under what title he pleaſe, ſhall attend ſuch acts in ſuch or ſuch Precincts, and with others judge in the caſe: The <hi>Presbyterians</hi> have nothing to oppoſe to it, provided things be fairly tranſacted, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged, according to the Rules of God's Word in the cauſe; but judge it a <hi>prudential act,</hi> conſonant to reaſon, and the will of God: But they can allow no <hi>ſingle perſon</hi> by any <hi>Divine Right,</hi> to have any ſuch power more than other.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Theſe being all the things that are purely <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> take not themſelves to be concerned, whom the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate</hi> pleaſeth to appoint to take care of <hi>Temples, Glebes,</hi> and <hi>Houſes</hi> or <hi>Tythes,</hi> or other <hi>Revenues given to maintain the Miniſtry,</hi> or giving <hi>legal inveſtitures in them, or hearing cauſes or queſtions about them;</hi> they being all <hi>Civil things</hi> within the <hi>Magiſtrates ſphere;</hi> as alſo what Titles of <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Dignity</hi> he will pleaſe to beſtow upon his Subſtitutes in ſuch truſts. They judge theſe things of no religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous nature, but ſuch as the Church hath been without in the beſt times, and may again be without, and yet exiſt the Spouſe of Chriſt: Nor are they at all concerned whom the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> will entruſt, and under what <hi>Titles</hi> to <hi>licence Phyſicians, Midwives, School-Maſters, Marriages,</hi> or to take any <hi>profits</hi> relating to ſuch things; they are <hi>Civil things,</hi> and in the Magiſtrates own diſpoſal, he may do with them what he pleaſeth; and <hi>Titles of Honour</hi> are his creatures; he may make what he pleaſeth, and diſtribute them to whom he pleaſeth.</p>
               <p n="15">15. They do judge there is an Officer of the Church alſo called a <hi>Deacon,</hi> and though the term in the <hi>Greek</hi> be of larger ſignificancy, yet they conceive the work of this Officer ſufficiently deſcribed and limited Acts 6. to take <hi>care of the poor;</hi> whoſe work it is to take care (by the <hi>voluntary almes</hi> of <hi>Chriſtians</hi>) to provide for <hi>the poor</hi> of his particular Church; they do not diſapprove, but highly applaud the care of the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> in appointing civil <hi>Officers</hi> and giving them a <hi>legal</hi> power to make <hi>equal rates</hi> for this end: but they ſay this <hi>Law was</hi> made for the <hi>hardineſs</hi> of <hi>mens hearts,</hi> for would people do their duty the poor of every congregation might (and that more acceptably to God) be provided for by the due care of the <hi>Officers of Churches,</hi> and the free <hi>contributions of people;</hi> when ever they meet together
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52746:8"/> to worſhip God, and the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate</hi> eaſed of the great burthen he hath upon him in that particular.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Cenſures of the Church.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THey know no <hi>Cenſures of the Church,</hi> but <hi>Admonition, Suſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> and <hi>Excommunication</hi> or Rejection: or as ſome delight ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſpeak. <hi>Admonition,</hi> and the greater and leſſer <hi>Excommunication.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. For <hi>Admonition</hi> they ſay there is a <hi>Brotherly Admonition,</hi> which is a <hi>charitable</hi> act whereby one <hi>Private Chriſtian</hi> reproveth his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, not <hi>ſuffering ſin upon him.</hi> 2. A <hi>Paſtoral Admonition</hi> which is the <hi>Act of the Miniſter,</hi> admoniſhing any under his charge, of any errors; which hath more authority in it than the other. 3. <hi>An Admonition, which is a Church cenſure,</hi> and is the <hi>Act</hi> of the whole <hi>Congregation,</hi> or the Officers of it as well in the name of Chriſt, as in their names, ſhewing a perſon, offending, his error from the word of God, and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting,</hi> and <hi>warning him to</hi> reform it. This they ſay may be often repeated.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They ſay a perſon under this cenſure ought not to be allowed all the priviledges of the Church, but to forbear the <hi>Holy Supper</hi> till he hath given ſome evidence of his <hi>repentance,</hi> and <hi>reformation</hi> ſatisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory to the Congregation.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Excommunication</hi> being the higheſt cenſure, they believe ought not be denounced <hi>by any perſons, but thoſe whom Gods Word hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed thereunto,</hi> nor <hi>for any crimes, but what the Word of God directs, nor in any other manner than it directeth.</hi> The perſons decreeing it muſt be the <hi>Church,</hi> by it's <hi>Officer</hi> or <hi>Officers,</hi> (they agreeing thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; for in vain is that perſon attempted to be caſt out of the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of a <hi>Church,</hi> with whom the members of that Church will have a communion) <hi>The crimes expreſſed in Scripture</hi> are <hi>pertinacious</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in <hi>hereſy,</hi> and ſcandalous living after <hi>reiterated admonitions</hi> and <hi>patient expectation of Reformation.</hi> As <hi>to the manner,</hi> the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture directs it to be done <hi>in meekneſs,</hi> after <hi>much waiting,</hi> and all due means uſed in order to <hi>Reformation.</hi> They do believe that all other <hi>Excommunications</hi> are but abuſes, and like the Mad-man's throwing about <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Darts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Hearing the Word and Prayers, being Religious Acts,</hi> to which <hi>Heathens</hi> and <hi>Publicans</hi> may be <hi>admitted,</hi> as deſigned for the <hi>conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:52746:8"/> or <hi>Reformation</hi> of Sinners, they do believe that Perſons <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated</hi> ought by the <hi>Divine rule</hi> to be admitted unto them, being perſons, who by the Apoſtles rule ought ſtill to be <hi>admoniſhed as Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> not <hi>accounted as enemies.</hi> 1 Theſ. 3. 15, 16.</p>
               <p n="6">6. When Perſons are <hi>Excommunicated,</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> can proceed no further, and have nothing to do, but to pray for them, and the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular members privately to <hi>admoniſh them,</hi> but they are ſtill as <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Subjects</hi> under the power of the Civil Magiſtrate if they commit, or perſiſt in any crimes under his cognizance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Civil Magiſtrate.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THey do with all thankfulneſs to God, <hi>own</hi> and <hi>Revere</hi> his Ordinance of <hi>Civil Magiſtracy,</hi> and are ſo far from encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon it. That they believe no Miniſter of the Goſpel ought to imploy himſelf in it. But to give up himſelf to <hi>Meditation</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> and the <hi>meer ſpiritual overſight</hi> of the flock of Chriſt commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the <hi>due form of Government, or power of Governours in any Nation,</hi> they believe <hi>Gods word hath fixt no univerſal Rule,</hi> onely confirming the juſt Laws of Kingdoms and <hi>Polities,</hi> and they believe it their duty to be obedient to ſuch <hi>Governours</hi> in all places, as the laws in that place have eſtabliſhed, and in the exerciſe of ſuch power as thoſe laws have given them. From the obedience to which no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon upon the account of Religion can pretend to an immunity; and in the exerciſe of which no Magiſtrate ought by any to be reſiſted.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But they believe it their duty, onely actively to <hi>obey Magiſtrates in ſuch things, which are not contrary to the Law of God;</hi> and whether they be contrary or no, (as to their own practice) they conceive their own <hi>conſciences muſt be judges;</hi> and as to ſuch things they conceive themſelves onely obliged to ſuffer <hi>the penalties</hi> for ſuch diſobedience peaceably. In ſhort they acknowledge themſelves bound to obey the Magiſtrate legally commanding in all things, wherein (ſo far as they are able to Judge) the word of God ſaith to all. <hi>Do it not.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:52746:9"/>
               <head>Concerning Matters of Faith.</head>
               <p>IN all matters of Faith. The Presbyterians believe whatſoever is in the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> the <hi>Nicene Creed,</hi> the <hi>Confeſſions</hi> of Faith of the <hi>Churches of God</hi> in <hi>Switzerland, Holland, France, Geneva;</hi> The <hi>Articles of Ireland,</hi> our own 39 <hi>Articles</hi> (with exception onely to the <hi>Articles</hi> concerning the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline:</hi> And defy the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines of <hi>Papiſts, Socinians, Pelagians, Semi-Pelagians</hi> and all others erring from the Faith.</p>
               <p>From this paper we truſt our Countrymen will underſtand: That the Principles of thoſe called <hi>Presbyterians</hi> (in the ſtricteſt notion of the term) are no ſuch things, but very good, and honeſt men may own, and the briskeſt tongues and pens of their Adverſaries will not be very forward to evince either to be <hi>unſcriptural,</hi> or <hi>Irrational.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
